<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>pandas on Ephemeral Dance Of Electrons</title><link>https://tmzh.github.io/tags/pandas/</link><description>Recent content in pandas on Ephemeral Dance Of Electrons</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2019 12:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://tmzh.github.io/tags/pandas/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Visualizing air routes for major airports using Spark and Matplotlib</title><link>https://tmzh.github.io/post/2019-01-05-using-spark-and-matplotlib-to-visualize-air-routes-for-major-airports-around-the-world/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://tmzh.github.io/post/2019-01-05-using-spark-and-matplotlib-to-visualize-air-routes-for-major-airports-around-the-world/</guid><description>&lt;p>In 2nd Century AD, Hellenic Cartographer Ptolemy was beset with an arbitrary choice of whether his maps should have north on the top or any other direction. Based in Alexandria, he reasoned that all population centers and places of importance lie to the north and would be convenient for study if they were in the upper right corner of the map. This arbitrary choice had long, unintended repercussions for mankind such as Australia being considered &amp;ldquo;Down under&amp;rdquo; or even our solar system to be perceived as rotating in counter-clockwise direction. Who would have thought that the stroke of a cartographer carried celestial importance!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Predicting the playing role of a cricketer using Machine Learning (Part 2)</title><link>https://tmzh.github.io/post/2018-04-28-predicting-the-playing-role-of-a-cricketer-using-machine-learning-part-2/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Apr 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://tmzh.github.io/post/2018-04-28-predicting-the-playing-role-of-a-cricketer-using-machine-learning-part-2/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the previous &lt;a href="https://tmzh.github.io/machine%20learning/2018/04/23/2018-04-23-predicting-the-playing-role-of-a-cricketer-using-machine-learning-part-1/">post&lt;/a> we saw how to scrape raw data from a content rich webpage. In this post, we will explore how to process that raw data and use Machine Learning tools to predict the playing role of a cricket player just based on his career statistics.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>